My name's andrew hall on the program manager for the visual security butter...on
the broader diagnostics team in visual studio we own debugging perf tools and tele
trace historical debugging and we
build the android emulator that you saw in the keynote this morning so a broad range of things that
we work on today we'll talk about debugging tips and tricks for dot
net developers envisage and fifteen we're going to hit on a...the new stuff that we've added in the
...and but a lot of it will be applicable across languages so everything
...show today is...dot net csharp it all works for
...as well but much of it would actually work for debugging cplus-plus
...debugging...ios or android using...or cplus-plus
...or something like that so little about myself after I graduated from college I went
wrote line-of-business apps for a couple years in
...dot net I went back to graduate school got my masters degree in computer
science and then had the opportunity to join the...team and microsoft I've been using the
...a vv dot net developer for years love the products as
an opportunity I couldn't turn down joined microsoft almost seven years ago
sudden working in this particular team for about seven years so why are we
all here todaysorry submit a
evaluation to for each one you tend to get entered to win a prize.
Where here?
I'm assuming every single-person in this room is here because you have to...your
day job and here's to quotes you can read really quickly but it turns out that we
spend a lot of time debugging problems one-word developer by trade.
you're not really any value when you're debugging problems right you actually get paid to
make things work you get paid right you features and functionality your application so any time
that you can save finding problems is actually time...being a better developer
so today I hope to show you some tips and tricks for how to get the most out of the debug
are define problems more quickly I don't think you're going to see anything that's going to
...your bug for-you we
...invented that button and we really haven't...the and the fix it for you button yet
but hopefully you'll come away with something that will help you understand.
Well, I've never seen that before, yeah, that would save me a lot of time so it's all about time saving tips and
tricks for the ability to find problems in your code faster.
So, the agenda I'm going to briefly show you for slides...things these are things
that I don't have time to talk about but there's a url at the bottom you can go grab the
slides afterwards you can go investigate them and all the contents going to be covered
and other talks so you have an opportunity either watch those or go watch them if they've already happened or
...tandem we're going to try to demo visual studio organize actually spend time in the
...with the product for about fifteen minutes and then at the end I put together
some slides of bonus multi-threaded tips if you do multi-threaded debugging these are
slides again with some call out for features you may or may not be aware of with urls where you can go
learn more about those...don't think we're going to have time to get to those today by some miracle we
do and we can take a look at those in the bagger as well as...sound like a good...everybody.
first thing I talked about new we've added a diagnostic tools window into the
...you've press f five with visual studio to start debugging the first-time if
...pick up the rc and download...you're going to see this pop-up off to the right
includes performance information
includes some historical information so we record when you break-in any bagger whether...a step
...break point in the enterprise skew we also pulling
the output window content and intelligence events if you're familiar
that feature this will be covered in both the performance
tools talk that I'm going to be giving tomorrow in conjunction with my colleague
envelope metropolis who's the program manager for intelligent race and he's giving a talk on
...on friday
...also be covering the intelligently specific functionality of this
so purpose anybody seen this yet and there's...two thousand fifteen.
Arms nobody so we brought timing information into the butter so as you step and run
between break points you can do order of magnitude measurements to figure out how longer code
...executes this is a really light way in the course of normal
development and debugging just get a ballpark idea for how long things take
to execute you don't want to use it for, you know, individual milliseconds but if you step over query to
a database and it takes six seconds it was pretty close to six seconds right so no more
...stop watches or trying-to time things that way in your.
And, that will be...the performance tools talk tomorrow evening a ui debugging tools,
for example,
these are tools that lets you do for wpf and the windows store apps
...inspect...visual tree and...properties while the applications running if
you're familiar with the browser tools you just say click on the element and I'll show you all
the properties we finally brought that into visual studio and then the last thing which you psychology keynote
this morning is visual studio has added support for android including csharp we
are partnership was...a check box in the visual studio two thousand fifteen rc that
ship today to say jan interested in doing...development...us android and mendoza
check that click installer go...down those bits install those for you so that's a very
quirk whirlwind tour of some stuff that's available to you that we're not going to talk about today.
All right so let's go ahead and jump over...start looking at visual studio as promised and
...as much time in the product as we possibly can so I have a wpf
application that I've written can people in the backseat...a big enough...nods
...and the idea was when it popped up I wanted to say hello
build because I'm node this is...be everybody's favorite talking build and I'm going to get asked to give
...again so I want to make sure that I can just via parameter
passing the application are the name of the menu...don't have to go
...change...have a command line parameter it says hello whoever I'm talking to but,
clearly it's telling me that I didn't actually provide the argument
correctly so what I want to do is I want to configure my project properties
to passes sand gino that you can configure your project properties in visual studio to set command line parameters
your applications so I'm going to write click I'm going to say properties and it's going to take
...project properties page there's quite a few options in here for the...
I can choose various start options so by default it's going to launch my project but if you have a
dl or something you can choose to...external program so if you're developing excel plug-in when you
...project by default it creates a dl and it has start external program and it
has excel listed here you can obviously start...the url as it says there we
have command line arguments you can configure working directory for application you can
set up remote debugging if you want remote of five to work and then you have some debugging options
here where you can enable native code debugging if you have some cplus-plus libraries that...as well
...check boxing every debugging your cplus-plus and dot net code...the same time you can even enable
sequel server debugging if you're doing communicating with see a server that way and
final option is enable the visual studio hosting process anybody here hosting processes.
Now okay so hosting process is an optimization the project system
does where for many dot application types it actually has your application already running
...loaded all of the framework assemblies that you've reference so you
press a five we start-up a lot faster every now and
then so this is going to be a little bit small my apologies
but you can actually see that there's a photo project archived that
...host here so my project is actually already running
if you go to your build output directory you'll see the name of your executable in this case product
archived that...dot eggs the and project...that if you have to the as host of
agnes this makes things...faster for you when
you're debugging enable some interesting scenarios using things like the immediate windows
...talk about...a little bit so...so I needed at a conference
flag here so this is build so now I'm expecting that when I
...this it should say hello bill.
Unfortunately the teleconference so I made a
bug somewhere in my applications not doing what I expect you to go in and figure out
where that particular piece of logic it's unfortunately
...in the course of coding quickly built up a couple of classes...my projects and set
a scrolling around and trying to find the right places...the break point my
project constructor I'm going to start debugging by stepping into my project so step into
...step overall have the same effect here f ten or eleven for people that are used using
the keyboard shortcuts so much you step into this
...bugging and...into the constructor my application so it
...automatically steps you into the...whatever applications that
you're next tip that you can start debugging with stepping which can be really,
really nice if you don't hunt find the break point for the particular entry point your application
somebody down here and it looks like on this particular line that building
my greeting string and it's doing a string concatenation it's doing to get
greeting get conference and get punctuationmethod call now because of
...method calls I can't just hover over them and get a nice dataset telling me what
the value is I could debugging each and every one of them or I could go manually type them into
the watch window but as a visual studio two thousand thirteen
...visual studio twenty fifteen when I step over that line of code
the autos window and noun visual...the locals windows well shows me what are called
return values so I can see all of the methods that I just stepped over the values
that those returns that's a really useful way to debug code.
Thank you.
...really useful feature when you're trying to understand obviously the applause...you see the
value so the other thing to note is if you're a watch window aficionado they're not going
to show up there but if you prefer to work in the...window we have something in the...called pseudo variables they
...dollar sign these are all documented but you can choose return value and...show you
the return value and it's a return value n so if I want the next return value can
...return value one and then two three four five
of thread many return values as their worth their four-month
...stop evaluates you can always just keep...dicey to variable if you prefer to spend your time and watch
window and that automatically evaluate for-you as well.
So, based on my return values here I was able to see that the
problem is that the get conference functionality
...the wrong things I want to debug down into that now anybody know
...statement...next statements a really useful piece of functionality burger that
let me move my execution context around so I don't have to restart application I've already
past this point so instead of having to stop
debugging restart I can simply write click in
choose set next statement which is down here control shift...the keyboard...
or I can just drag it in the gutter over here and now execution
will do that the only thing to note is that this does not change the state of your application it's not
...truly simply moves the execution stream you'll notice
that greeting here if I have rover it has a value it's not know because it was assigned last on
...sine of this line I'm simply going to re-execute the
...so if you have certain things that can only execute one-time where they have side effects
...next statement will not undo not avoiding a side effects.
now I'm here I want to debug into the get conference function I could
...go navigate down to the definition celebrate point
f five and down to it that way or I could step into the get...function
first then come out then step back and the conference but I have another handy feature using any
...I'm right clicking I'm going to go to this thing that's a step in a specific and this is
...a one a list of all the method calls on that line so this only works for dot
net talk but we have list of all not all method calls so I can choose to get conference
...going to do is
set a one-time break point on the entry point to that method and it's going to run
execution to that point stop...me and I...conference it executes to that point
...out into a specific methods so this is you can see the utility of that
...you're dealing with align has one method calls on it so now I want to get
down here I can see that I'm doing a comparison looking for where the parameter equals
conference so instead of setting break point running down there and deleting it I'm going to use another
feature to control my execution that's called run to cursor and there's a really useful
feature raises all the times my favorite features in the butter which learn how to use it and control
...ten is the keywords...times I just clicking control left-hand rather than...click but when you run
...cursor it runs execution that point says one-time break point right didn't have
to celebrate point and then delete the break point and it looks like what I've done here
is the parameter is conference and there's a space and you get conference name and I really
want args of x plus one...fixes and I want to
...and a nice robust way and...use a feature that we call editing continuing the
bagger which is the ability to edit code while I'm stop...butter
...five have a continue running mit changes are going to be applied so let's go ahead
and fix this going to go x plus one and now I'm going to hit
...debugging step over.
All right conference here is bill it's exactly what I wanted to be so I
fix my bug and now what I want to do is I...get back out
of this particular function and I can do that by using
the step out features anybody here if you step out and debugging about half the
...hand if you're not aware that the
...has a step out feature that's going to bring me back up to.
Exactly the last instruction that method finished executing so now if I
two-step in again I'm not going to go past that
line code because I literally came back out to the point that I entered if I
...here...actually going to get punctuation function and element
...eleven I'm going-to be down further down everybody here uses the
setup feature did, you know, that you can use the run to cursor on-call stacked in deep cost
...to achieve the same functionality so I'm notice
...methods down here I'm going to write click on my main window I'm going to choose
run the cursor and it's going to run back up the call stack to the point that
entered that so notice I was down to methods step out what
brought me up one but run to cursor in the context of the call
stack window will actually bring me all the way back up to wherever I chose to write
clips that can be a good way if you're in a deep call stacked unwind that quickly.
All right.
briefly here's a here's...quicker...things that we talked about that work for people that's kind
...the thing that we're going to do for about the next forty minutes so hopefully that's useful to you.
All right so let's go back to the product.
Right so now we have this particular application up and running...go ahead and restarted to make sure
...nice fresh start I'm what is jpf applications ultimately going to do
...connector web server and it's going to
...some information this is an application that I've been developments colleagues
...trying to get an inventory of all the sample code that we have from we do events like this the first thing...do...just want
to test the loading of my data so I have a button here that's going to say
load data and it's going to go down and it's going to break and it's going to break
...if you look at the code it said...buttered... you can imbed break points in
your code using debugged outbreak you don't have to just set them from the
ide so you can actually hard to break points in there now the interesting thing about hardcopy break point in
...know what happens is I have a debugged up break-in there are run without any butter.
It crashes the application so break point is actually a special type
of exception that's understood to be a break point so without any...attached you
...exception its on handled the application crashes so I've also wrapped
inside of this property called...dot is attached so this is something
...you can do your application where you can actually code
for debugging where you can say hey if on debugging I want this to happen so in this case from
debugging I want to break but I don't have a debug attached
don't execute this steward...breaker don't behave in some other method and actually a lot of the windows store
up templates have this logic in their in certain places will turn
on extra diagnostics tracing if you have any if is
debugged attached turn on some pra additional tracing or if
debugged attach debugged outbreak in certain failure paths where exception
...it thrown handled and re from somewhere else...catch
...they'll actually do this to use your application doesn't just disappear, you know,
what's going on so that's other
...for you so I have my data provider up here my data provider looks
like it's been correctly and initialized well hopefully let's dig in and look at it didn't
air out and I can see there's quite a bit of data in here so,
I have some properties...looking at the...property and it looks like
there's stuff in there but...get a better view of it then I can see here...the data tipper down
to watch window you'll see this little magnifying glass over here to the right and
the magnifying glass indicates that we have a visualize
...cyclic magnifying class it's going to open a different view on top of that data
as little down arrow so we have four built-in text visualize
...the product as a visual studio two thousand thirteen update here we have
a normal text visualize are the just visualize any string you can choose
rapping or not...it's up to you comment although in this case is
...data so the string text analyzers going to do me a lot of good so I'm going to
go ahead and select the json visualize
are and this is going to pop up and it's going to let me explore my json a nicely formatted
manner...support search so I can see I have an...type of web so if I want to
search for all places that I have web you can see that happens and that's going to happen very quickly.
And, the next time I come back here it's going to remember...room
...the wrong thing it can actually remember that I had selected the json visualize are so you don't have to
select the visual a different visualize
are every time once you selected we're going to remember what you selected for that variable for the lifetime
that visual studio instance so that was the json visualize
...so now let's go down...xml data so we have an xml visualize are
giving sy formatting on the xml.
We have...html visualize as well so it's going to
format html for me which makes that a lot more readable and then up here
it says application dataset so this is a dataset I can
see system that data dataset the only one visualize available for this the dataset visualize
...when I open that that's available to me as well so that lets me
explore all the data in my dataset very useful and dealing with databases and then the last visualized
...big into the product that I wanted to talk about is the
...fertilizers if I go down to my autos window I can see that this is here this is
my wpf name window so we have a...tree visualize are built individual studio for that
when I open it up I can explore the visual tree down...the bottom left I can see
a rendering of whatever element I have selected and then over on the right I can
explore the properties for any of those given elements so those are the six
...that we bacon by default that are owned by the corgi
butter team in visual studio you can write your own it's really not that hard
msdn talks about has documentation how-to-do-it so if you're interested you deal with
the certain complex data structure frequently it'll take an hour to write a visualize are
for it maybe well worth your time in terms of debugging think about trying debugged
dataset using just drilling through data tips versus having a nice visualize are for...
All right so now I'm
...explores looks like my data has gotten initialize somewhat correctly but I
want to look at these apps the list that are coming back that's really important information that's what I'm going to
be dealing with and my first thing is I've certainly this array as I have this
thought I really wish that I had some more useful
...this particular the burgers view of this so I'm going to go in and I'm going to tell the bow
...the app how to present itself to the butter the classed definition
instead...navigating I'm going to write click and I'm going to choose peat definition most
...familiar with...twelve...definition we also have functionality in visual studio called
...definition that's going to just open this little window in the middle...editor and salami to
...file without having to have the big context which to jump...particular case I want
to add a debug are display and I don't have the right
things of tip most people hopefully know this but if not control dot is going to give median teller
sense for that so...I hit enter it's
...go ahead and add the correct using for me and then now when I come in I'm going to specify the
...display attribute it takes a string as a parameter I can type plain old
...so in all type app and I'll...just...app to me...I put
...curly braces is going to evaluate the property on top
from the particular applications somebody say app type in this case or let's say
at name and see I have this intelligence dialogue covering stuff up very helpful
...becomes transparent.
So, anytime you...have a pop-up in the id if you don't want to go away but you also
...remember what's under control transparent.
Let us control and it comes back up right so now I've
...app name you'll see these little red squiggles that's telling me that I can't actually apply this via
...continue display attribute has to be rebuilt so that's okay I'm the
click the restart debugging button you don't have to manually stop-and-go
click restart we actually have a nice restart debugging button for you I'm going to come back I'm going to
have over apps and now...expanded by adding
...display attribute it's telling the...how it should present that data to me so
seen app abs zero app one at two-out-of-three out for et cetera et cetera so I can put anything I want
to over display...there's also other debug
...star attributes that you can go look up on msdn
...cover them but you actually even go right additional classes that choose how to
format the class that you're looking at so...that exist for some of the framework types?
So, now that we're insider
are data tip I mention this early with the intelligence but works for data tips as well
as main investment in drilling down and I press control it goes transparent
marginalize kind of fun doesn't really making more product productive but if you're
ever city your computer and kind of tired and you just want to play.
It'll make you happy and then notice that I had this whole...icon over here
...anybody ever pinned data chipped in visual studio about half the less
than half the room so you click the...icahn it's going to stick
...the editor for me so now it's here I can do whatever I want with it someone
...head down here I'm a set of break point and I'm going to run to this particular break point and I'm going to look at the
app this is particularly useful the ability to pin these things when you're dealing
iterative situations I find myself using them and loops a lot so now here is a hit si
...remembering great point I can just watch the value
update I can manually add expressions...if I wanted additional stuff
...expression and I can do app data.
Display.
Languages and that'll evaluate for me so I can build-up my own
little watch inside the editor if I want I can even make comments if I'm trying to
debugged really hard problem and I'm trying to remember what the previous values where I can say,
you know, so, this case app...tight equals csharp if that's helpful to
me and now I hit go out here and I'm going to run to the next break point and now it's going to
Type equals...can take from looks like that and collapse
am you can expand them they come back you can even float
...if you have multiple put them somewhere that they're really out of the way like up here.
So, the question is...get save with the project they do get save with
the solution...save the same place...break points at so now I come back
...show one more thing I can backer the editors I can pin this again when I
stop debugging you're...to see that it's still remembers that
they're there and when I hover over it it's going to show me the value from the last
...sessions this can be kind of handy stop debugging...icon is going to show your previous values?
So, let's go ahead and.
Come back right...here.
Talked about these will go ahead and get rid of that
now I don't need that so now I'm down here in my watch windows let me say I want to build-up some state
of my watch window and let's go ahead and drill in on...app, you know,
that you can add things to the...window from here so I might want to say
...id and I can say add watch.
And, then down here I might have app and it can even do that from the watch window
itself I have state and I'm particularly interested in so owner maybe I just want
to make this a top-level attribute so I'm going to say
Scroll up collapse this and now
...it's nicely there what happens if I need to watch this
some operating on this app but I'm going to step into...get languages for display what's going to happen everything
I watch window I'm going to lose the ability to see what its properties
were windows particular variables are not scope even though they're still in memory and theoretically and
...step back out of this and I'm going to use a feature that is going to allow me to
track the object even when the variable name is not and scope so we get
compiler
slits track the app id and I'm going to write click on it and I'm going to choose.
A functionality.
That is called.
I can...find it make object id there we go to this particular one...of the one
...primitive but see if...real object...to make object...notice
...dollar sign...of the right of it for those of you have you who
...uses feature prior twenty fifteen...a syntax has changed a little bit we used to use
a hash tags there's a couple reasons we made that change first of all we
had inconsistent syntax between visual basic and csharp now both of them use
the dollar sign number for the object...if I go create more object
...that will have one-two-three-four five six and the other reason is we talk about
suitor variables already it was consistent with the debugged concept
of pseudo variables now I'm going to go down here and I'm going to type dollar sign one and when
I stepped into this get languages for display helps...a step in and not step over?
You're going to see that all these other variables are...scope but I can still actually see
the value of the dollar sign one so make object id is a features allows
you to track your objects if you want to see their values...in memory, you know,
...valid but you might be stopped in the...in a place where you can actually access them by.
So, that's a
tip for that and then I can write click and I can say delete object id if I'm done with that.
So,...I have to watch all right so.
Let's come back over to powerpoint very briefly.
There's a very brief review of the tips and tricks that talked about in
this particular context there any questions so far.
That's the question was why don't you have debugged outbreak only attached when.
...have the logic to only break when...is actually...about the dot net frameworks I don't
hundred-percent...speculate but speculative talked to people that actually have found
...to be a useful thing sometimes to actually crash their application you have a
code that like it almost...like a not...not implemented exception
...it's a great question I don't actually know it comes from the system from the runtime...not added by our team.
Great question...me back to visual studio for that for
demo number three the question was if I use the
...dependable data tips that can I share those are just go into
my solution...answers by default it just goes into your solution
but on the debug menu you can actually...if
...down export your pin data tips and share those with a colleague so by
default they're just save your project but you can take an explicit action so-if you built up some
interesting debug state and you wanted to export those data tips you can do that with
your comments and all they can import them...will go to the same source...files
that you were on you can also export break points that's another thing I wasn't going to show
...from the...of exporting...can theoretically exporter break point along with the data
...say hey import this process five you'll hit this and you'll see
the data tips that I builds up with their state...action required.
Right so let's go ahead and move on past ...my break point here.
And, we'll go ahead and restart debugging just to come in a nice clean state.
So, now we validated the data is getting loaded correctly I've
written some test to make sure that what I'm going to do is I
have a secure communication boundary between the client-server so
my tess are going to encode mine parameters...passing up they're going
to be decoded on the other side I'm not actually going to make the web...case but I'm going to test
the libraries themselves and make sure that everything works correctly so when I click my run
test button I can see that two of them succeeded and one of them failed
someone jump in and debug this so if I go down here
have my run tests method so many go ahead and jump into this get apps by
And, this which is where the codings occurring I know that
...only failing for desktop remember so I could you have a couple options that I can
do here option a would be I could celebrate point I could hit
it I could sort of watch and I can just wait till the value got to...wanted or I can
...break point I'll ask the bagger to only stop when the value equals what I want
equal notice I have a disabled break point here that can be
a nice sort of way to bookmark things if you're not interested in them but,
notice when I celebrate point now vision fifteen issues...toolbar pop up here
so to wireless you disable...break point and it also lets you open the
break point settings which appears and non-verbal...
We have a couple settings you can apply...apply conditions so we
have a conditional expression this is conceptually anything you could type in
if statement so in this particular case actually need to move my break point down one-liner
...the wrong line so I'm...I can adjust that year I can just do line twenty-three instead of
having to delete it and it's going to jump there is a cork that doesn't rearrange itself but
...so you can move a break point and synonymous ignition expression I want to say
decoded type notice I'm getting intelligence...here just like you would expect.
And, that's a desktop.
So, now.
When I run this again notice that the?
...mobile execute version and desktop execute
...click my run test button and when I stop going to see that my decoded type
...desktop so the conditional break point has stop me only one I asked that
...so that conditions...satisfied if you're wondering the other conditions available to you
are we have the concept of hit counts...this is purely based on the number of times of the break points
and hit you can choose to do it based
on equals is a multiple of more greater than equal to so sometimes well?
I find useful in certain situations to go, yeah,
I know I want to stop the first-time I get here...to be hate taiwan then I'll have to remember delete my
break point because I'm guessing like many of you I a
lot of times forget to separate points I want to debugging something I go okay I think at working
...five let's go tested again...stop it all these very points I forgot I
headset so ...account can be useful way to make sure you stop once you don't have to remember...the...
break point often and then we have something on a filter break point which is in my
slides multi-threaded tips baby about debugging code this running parallel so you can see the conditions are based
on machine process or thread information and I can combine these so I
could do a conditional expression in conjunction with the...count and that would work.
And, then we'll talk about the actions ...a little bit so now that we're in this place
...stopped the desktop and I can see the...type equals desktop I
...double-check because I'm pretty sure that there's applications of tag desktop in here
so one way would be to go drill through this applications list and look
...be a lot nicer if I could just query this.
So, what I'm going to do and
...I actually wanted to do here was not that but that's okay somebody who had
the immediate window this would work in the wash or the locals or any other windows but I'm going
to type a...say data dot applications?
Select.
A baptized moi.
...works so as a visual studio two thousand fifteen you can
now evaluate lambda expressions and all of the butter...windows.
even better or perhaps just as good I think I see my bug and
then is desktop as capital d here desktop has a lower-case
d in this particular case and might equals has not asked to be case invariant now
wouldn't it be awfully great if I could apply
edit continue to my lambda expression as a visual studio two thousand fifteen rc...
Screen comparison dot...case.
Puts it...five and it best.
We fix...edit continue for lambda expression lambda expressions in
...indeo undone thank you.
All right so now we've got that working.
I want-to make sure that my I things actually work when I try to query
the server so I'm going to...this get apps and this is not going to actually make my first call out
of the server that we've looked at today and it goes and goes and it's between error occurred
...server that make sense the servers another project that's in my visual studio
solution and I forgot to started so instead of having to go back and do a lot of brigham rolls,
you know, that...project I can write click on the project
say debug start you instance it's now going to use dirt?
...I know what problem is it this is the...but I just edit
...shared between the two projects so it wasn't happy with it couldnt rebuild it for the
web server so sorry that's one of the right so gaps it's going to fail.
Solutions for number right click now I'm going to say debug
...vincent's that will work correctly so now I come back here and
...get apps I can quick start...couple seconds because web server has
...up and everything work correctly so debug start new
...a little tip if you're doing working with multiple projects but that's going to be kind of a pain to...
do frequently so what I'd prefer to happen is I prefer to have a web server launch every time that I
started debugging so I'm going to go to my project properties and I'm going
...solution properties now not the into projects and I'm going to go to
this startup project tab and I can configure multiple projects to
start-up I can choose to start them with the...or I can choose to start them without
the butter so if I wasn't particularly interested in the web server but I just
needed to make sure that started I...they start with...debugging every time I...debugging
...application it's not going to start debugging the web application that's actually a
...that's okay I'm okayed debugging it in this particular case
...go onset this break point now.
everything's working great up to this point the next piece of functionality that I would like is if you see this
app type drop down I want-to make sure that I can filter by the various
...so-if
...mobile expected to only show me the mobile and I'm doing all of this logic server-side
let's.
Go ahead and see what happens when I try desktop.
Anime getting nothing we just proved...lambda expressions that there are actually applications of
...desktops what's going on it's go ahead and jump over
to our server-side code and debugged.
So, actually...go ahead into this at data provider directly rom decoding it again
and make sure everything is correct remember this library shared between the two of them and I
come down here I'm going...break point.
And,...head appear this and have to use?
And, then I'm going to go try...hit the desktop again
...I break I...decoded desktop after I've
on encrypted it is actually coming through I'm losing the
p for some reason so that's why I'm not finding anything how do I figure this out I have
a library that's doing all my encoding for me it's encrypting and decrepit
...the string.
...going to tell you that the problems actually down and down
...that particular layer so we're going to go find are.
The functions down here that actually are going to do is the
...shifting on my characters as...encoding them what I want to do is a
long string I don't want to debug and stop and
...break point inspect every time I want to just be able to dump all this information so I'm going to go
...choose actions and I'm going to set what visual studios refer to as a
trace point where I'm going to print a message to the output window and then
...resume execution so when it encodes in decode
the strings and desktop I'm not going to stop at all I'm just going to have a record of everything that
happened the output window and there's three types of tests that I can
type I can type plain old text so here I'm going to say shush.
And, then anything I put in curly braces much like the debugged espy
...going to be evaluated so I want to say ...to masking
...intelligence you expect and that's going to go to.
The value of...and then we have pseudo variables again here
...sign and I can choose to output relevant information about the
project you can see what they are call stack is an interesting one sometimes if you don't know-how you're
getting the various places you said...trace point you can ask it to...the call stack...going to
dump the function because we can...go ahead and close and then I'm going to set
an equivalent trace point down here where I'm uninteresting
the string and I'm going to say decoding.
we're going to...the same thing we're going to say by eight to unmanned ask.
Went to.
Not unchecked on...
that...work for me so I can either leave this open this is a nice non modal...window if you ever
uses functionality and prefers visual studio you remember all of the functionality for conditions and
actions within...completely separate dialogues
...theoretically combine of all but you had to write click open mobile...couldn't copy
...editor...interactive my editor if I want I can close if I want now when I go
ahead and start debugging and I'm going to click the...
I'm going to choose desktop.
And, you're going to see the particular string that I had output
here of my break points set from before but that's okay.
I have a record of everything that was encoded and decoded so
...points I find really useful when you iterative things like this and you need to understand is actually really hard
and given point time to stop and get the full picture and remember I'm dropping the...so I can see that it's
being encoded the last characters been encoded has been encoded
one twelve it's been decoded are...from one twelve the
thirty-eight...actually been decoded from thirty-seven to one eleven so
...when it's been crossed...across that web boundary
...modifying the character and if I go look at my
...table it turns out that character thirty-eight
is in ampersand which is a special character so it hasn't been
escape shows the browser actually in process of...making the web request is changing
...to fix this particular issue and I want
to fix that down here before actually.
Without stopping I'm not going...continue in this particular case I
am going to rather use the ability to
simply modify variables so it's go ahead and come back out here.
Desktop and this particular functionality supports
bass sixty-four which will not have any special characters...
modify the value of this in the bagger
...five continue debugging and everything works correctly so it's another feature in the
bagger is that you had the ability to edit values directly
in memory which can be a great thing to test
...hypothesis as opposed to stop change the value right if you
want to see what happens to this conditional branch...I...this out or make it someone key value
and you can do that directing the debug or you don't need to stop and modify code every time...
Any further.
Questions.
So, the question if I understand question you're asking I was debugging
client in server how do I know which one I'm scoping too and I said the...
So, you all the break point will be hit unless you apply a filter
any process that hits...are any thread that hits...multi-threaded debugging is going to always stop on the
break point the watch is going to always evaluate in the context of the
...that the current is currently...by default...the one that you hit the
...point honor stepped on so you are able to so,
go back to the product really quick so it's go ahead and just click another button
soon by default...I have...what this particular thread
here's another tip I have the debug location toolbar...visible this comes by
default the general profile I don't think it was by default in the other ones but I can actually see all the threads that I'm
on so if I switched to a different thread someone
main thread if I go to this system events thread you're
going to actually see in the local
and watch window that and I can evaluate any of these things because I now
...the debugged of the context of the different threat that answer questions.
Array so...go ahead and just move on while we're here.
And, onto our last demo of the day so.
Vassar demos so I've gotpretty far along in this app
building together...now loads correctly my tests all pass seems
that works correctly across the web boundary via my encryption anti-christian so it's nice
and secure but what happens if for some reason something goes wrong.
And, you saw this perform the server wasn't running error occurred contact
and server what I want...I want to debugged to stop and tom with problem is
when I first had my first job doing...development I didn't know-how to make the debug
...stop for me when exceptions occured so it actually go
into my application and I'd find my try catches and
...comment them out so I'm guessing everybody here is done that at
some point fortunately in the bagger we have the ability to
...exceptions if you have not seen this yet how many people here before
...use the...exception settings in visual studio how many people here
...got coffee while the window came up.
Well, fortunately visual...fifteen we
...the window is light in fast and it actually has a respectable search.
So, for those of you who are not familiar with functionality what excuse me ability
do is I can write click and I can...right like I can checked particular
...groups of exceptions and I can ask the...to break whenever the exception is
throne as opposed to...behavior the debug of only break-even exceptions on
handled so in this particular case now we're running...go I've now
asti vertebrae can any common language runtime exceptions this is dot net for those who may not
know we call the dot net runtime the common language runtime of
...here referred to as both.
So, when I open my may window and I click my error this time it's going to
stop me down here where the error actually occurred
so awesome that's useful functionality to be able to stop without having to go
in find my trying catchers comment them out and get the debugged actually stop me and this is in
asic programming it's even more important because how many people here doing
...programming with await and tasks how many people here may have ever gotten burned
by this particular
piece particular problem that even if I don't try catch it?
Anybody tell me now where
mine app is going to stop.
When I hit the exception?
All right let's look and see what happens.
A versions exceptions are so on...returns off.
So, now the and handle exception will actually bring me back up to where
I'm waiting on the asynchronous call.
Our apologize in advance for this something I would like to fix
for-you in future given way...net runtime works...incredibly hard problem to
solve so for now the appropriate way to diagnose where exceptions are
current inside of asynchronous message you need to come into the exception settings
and enable first chance exceptions so let's go ahead and restart
...one more time.
Says go ahead and say...one more thing I want to show you a lot of people
...asynchronous code how many people here...aversion visual so-you older than twenty thirteen.
Very few people that a couple people so many people here have seen...we
...thirteen and it's called the asic call stacks.
So, I'm going to show another quick...you know,...
the visual studio actually has a third ide mode and it's called the
full-screen mode of the id and it remembers your window layouts just like
it does between debugging design-time...I go debug windows fyi already
...windows are under debug windows we see a lot of people in ux studies
ago looking for them on the human new and other
windows a reasonable place to look but it's not very useful because they're not there but,
now I can open the call stack window and I've haven't
docked over here I did this before the session...I had these pseudo
frames call anything that's in square brackets and great out...frame...the cost of
...asic call and this was we know that and asynchronous call occured
...awaiting on something is actually running on different task so prior visual studio
twenty thirteen before introducing this feature the only call stack that I would have seen
this particular case would have been that what we've done is by
introducing asic...stacked functionality we...you understand when you stop somewhere
unexpected or your debugging...how did I did
...via my code flow not just what's the current call stack of the current
...that's...think that's a really useful piece of functionality as well and
...thing on note...we're in the cost ecuador two more things is we have this
concept external code external code means that visual studios hiding a
bunch of group from the runtime for-you a feature that we call just my code just my
code and dot net controls both stepping so if I try to step into this http web
...is part of the framework it's going to be treated like a step over and then
the call stack looks much more pleasant if I want to turn that off I can shoot right click and I can say
show external code and now you understand why we have just my code.
So, that's what that's what it does for you and that's what that little gray...bracketed square bracket
thing external code us that means that the burgers hiding framework code from you that we don't think
is particular useful to-you...note is you can configure other options
and your call...view you can choose to show parameter values it's
awfully default I but so, normally would look like this when I choose...on it's going to show
...if I don't think the parameter names are particularly useful because I
have my code so I can...like this so I can just have the values the only thing to note
is we turned values on the reason...off by default you will incur some performance penalty evaluating the
caustic just like evaluating things in the watch window the
...has to do work to get the value of that...a lot of parameters or parameters that are expensive to
evaluate that will slow down every time you stop debugging so either...break
...step if.
You have the call segment...visible obviously we don't evaluate them
if we don't need to so we go ahead and turn off parameter values turn on parameter
...that's the fault state.
And, radio now...for screen mode my id
goes back to the same view that I had for so that's another great tip is the
view full-screen mode in the debug.
So, last thing I wanted to talk about lot of people
...hand they deal with asynchronous codes how many people here are use the tasks window.
If you few people so the tasks window is will show you all
...running tasks and implicitly any
...asynchronous functions are actually tasks
so-if you have something hong or you're trying to understand the relationship of what the state
of your tasks are you can open debug windows tasks just like the rest of
our windows and...show you all the...so in this particular case I'm in the
task that's doing the web request and then I have my
to other asynchronous methods are actually awaiting and...tell me which
tasks awaiting on so in this particular case the...from web a saying is a
...on task id two seven three which happens to be the active one and
task to seven-six...to seven-five which is the asynchronous method
...called so that's a...if you haven't used it but you're dealing with tasks and asynchronous code
...that's functionality that's also available to you in the butter it's
another window that are telemetry shows us not many people fine so I'm going to make sure to call that out.
All right so brief review of the things we
...that's going to conclude the demo portion of our talk today
...about five minutes left so other any questions before we move on.
The question was does make object aidid prevented garbage collector from
collection variable my recollection is yes it will.
Prevent the garbage collector from collecting that because we have to ac and additional reference to it so we can
tracking questioner.
Lockerbie moi.
So, the question was endings you fails from a whole lot is...general rule
or others...exceptions the answer was there were a
bunch of exceptions as a visual two thousand fifteen rc we have a
remove the vast majority of those exceptions you'll see the blog post today that talks about
the lambda support is a blog post when we really see bsix talked about the ability to do it in a
...all of a new csharp six language features so,
it's now more of a smallest of exceptions if you have blocking issues definitely let us know
...so...few limitations like you can't edit inside of catch...still is one limitation,
for example,...I promise you a few slides
...tips parallel stacks window url go check it
out threads window this...offers a lot of interesting functionality for...threads including the ability to
...improv freeze and thaw threads that will let you for sure threads in
...particular state so get to a certain point...it's not going to run past that...different
...different point freezes you can try to simulate what particular race conditions would be
...that particular way...additional multi-threaded tips share threads
insource run selected threads to cursor debug location to
...and I mentioned the filter break point and we briefly discussing
...toolbar I apologize I realize I forgot one thing off here so
...verbally inserted we also have a featuring the ide called the parallel watch
window the parallel watch window allows you to see all of
your threads that are executing in parallel since we have about four minutes to people
want to...real quick awesome so let's go back to visual studio.
Let's close some windows.
Let's go get the button that will show it to is visible.
Come down here you should be visible.
And, then now when I go.
...I take val example.
Solution explorer.
...going on here to never utilities so what I'm going to do in this particular case is I'm going to
try to calculate some prime numbers and I'm going toparallel because, you know,
calculating prime numbers can be extremely expensive which is why encryption actually
works somerset break point and I'm going to talk going-to go ahead and...as a hit
count
so the threads can kind of ramp up and get their all the threads can be spun up let's make it equal
...seven hundred so let's go boom.
Back here...click my button parallel.
...tip really quick I mention the conditional expression hit
...faster than conditional expression because...has to do less work
to if you're in a situation where you happen to know the count like it's a iteration...x variable, you know,
for into I...if you can use the hit count...be a little faster than that
conditional expression I showed you but some...the debug I'm going to go
open the windows and I'm going to open the parallel stacks first.
Is going to open up here so this is going to show me all the particular threads and the
other window that I wanted to show you is I want to show you let's go ahead and run...cursor
...in here?
So, I can get inside here the feature called the parallel watch window
and what this says is going to show me all of the values of objects
a variable across all of the various threats?
So, I can see the number of threads that I have running I can see the value of I on all the various
threats.
And, one more cool little tip while we actually happen
to be here is the immediate windowed you-can call random code from the
...window so stirring utilities and I'm going to call a reverse
string method that's going to execute recursively and most may say hello.
It's going to break point so...stop another break point I can debugged other methods we call this
...debugging and now in this particular case in the case of incursion
let's run down here I happen to be in the first break point which was a hit...as
I mentioned before let's run...cursor the end of my recursion if you see my call stack
...this many threads deep when I open...parallel
...window...is not a valid expression this
particular case but tr is I can see the value of the parameter all the way
up the recursion stack so that is the last
two bonus tips for you for the for the conference so.
...conduct me afterwards I want to get through we only have about a minute left but ...answer
questions afterwards...also get the visual city...boots up on the third-floor immediately after this
...clear out here's link to our blog...a couple of the related talks
mentioned all be giving a performance tools talk half of one tomorrow evening and then my
colleague envelopes will be talking about the historically bugging capabilities and lastly evaluate
the session have you found it useful please go give me a good reading so they let me come back to future conference.